costigag@tcd.ie

gcostigan.com

Working in the most competitive and notable research institutes in Europe has given me strong team working skills, with a focus on attaining the end goal using innovative techniques and tools. Now I am focusing my attention on applying my data skills in an industrial environment to solve a much wider world of questions.

EXPERIENCE

Data Science Fellow

S2DS with Pivigo, London Aug. 2017 – Sept 2017 As intern with SNTV, a world leading sports news video content provider, I was working on a 5 weeks, time boxed, data project to do a detailed customer segmentation and associated assement of resource allocation.

- · Part of a team of 3 which carried out first in-depth data analysis of content broadcast and download data.
- · Performed customer segmentation in order to deepen understanding of how SNTV's content is used and identify undervalued and/or ineffective content.
- · Provided further understanding of change in market due to rise in digital media and how this affects SNTV clients.
- Building of recommendation system to provide individual recommendations for SNTV clients.

Main Technologies: Python (scikit learn)

Skills: Customer Segmentation. Identifying Market Trends. Statistical Analysis. Clustering. Recommender Systems.

Travel & Personal Development

May 2016 – Aug 2017

During this period I traveled through latin america learning Spanish and volunteering.

Research Associate

Leiden University May 2014 – May 2016 Participated in the development of 'Big Data' (1 PB) scientific data archive – latest european astronomical all sky survey.

- Took a lead role in beta testing of archive: co-organised a team of 10 scientific testers, gathered amateur astronomer testers, collated all test cases and implemented and tested these in SQL. I then raised issues and liaised with the European Space Agency (ESA) archive development team to identify areas of weakness within the archive access software.
- Worked alongside ESA and private companies to develop archive tools: established companies had access to necessary data, understood archive contents and limitations of data (while limited data sets available).
- · Wrote the long term data preservation plan, contributed to testing of data traceability and to the collection and validation of data.
- Designed and supervised multiple student projects, Msc and PhD level taking place over time periods of 3-6 months.
- Produced high impact research contributing to over 15 published works which together are cited over 400 times.

Main Technologies: Python. SQL. R. Bash. Unix/Linux. Skills: Statistical Analysis. Data Wrangling. Data Validation. Experimental Design. Functionality design.

EXPERIENCE -

Junior Researcher

ESO. Munich DIAS, Dublin Oct. 2009 - Nov. 2013 Based between four different research institutes while working towards my PhD in astronomy, I developed effective communication skills, an independent work ethic and good project development skills.

- Performed rigorous testing for biases within data, cleaning methods and analysis.
- Learnt to work as an effective team member locally and remotely.
- · Awarded three research grants together worth over € 100,000.

Main Technologies: MIDAS (FORTRAN based). IDL.

Skills: Time Series Analysis. Data Visualisation and Communication. Data Cleaning.

Junior Researcher

Space Lab, Dundee University, Scotland Oct. 2008 - Oct. 2009 Implementing and testing of computer vision algorithms for planetary rover navigation.

Main Technologies: MATLAB/Octave.

Skills: Algorithm implementation and development.

EDUCATION –

PhD Dec. 2014

Graduated Queen's University Belfast (Northern Ireland)

Masters 2007 – 2008

Cambridge University (UK), Master of Mathematics. CASM Part III

Bachelors 2003 – 2007 Trinity College Dublin (Ireland), Theoretical Physics, BA (mod)

TECHNICAL SKILLS -

+ [beginner] ++ [intermediate] +++ [expert]

Python. +++

R. +

SQL. ++

BASH. +++

Unix/Linux. +++

MATLAB/Octave. ++

MIDAS (FORTRAN based). ++

IDL. ++

Git. +

Jira. +

AWS (EC3, Lambda, S3). +

COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT-

Feb. 2017 - Now

DataKind, Dublin.

DataKind is a group of data science volunteers working together to help not-for-profit organisations. Part of the work is to demonstrate and educate the NGOs on the power of data science and what it can be learnt from it.

Skills: NPL. Google Analytics.

Sept. 2016

Bogotá, Colombia.

Science teaching in a primary school as part of a three week voluntary placement. Designed and implemented program for all classes which involved 150 kids.

-Languages

English (native). Spanish (certified B2.4)

Personal Interests -

Kite surfing, Traveling, Food, Fitness, Teaching and Learning new things.